<!DOCTYPE paper SYSTEM "extremepaper.xml.dtd" >
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="extreme.html.xsl" ?>
<paper>
<front>
<title>The Resource Directory Description Language (RDDL): What goes at the end of a namespace URI?</title>
<author contact="1">
  	<fname>Jonathan</fname>
	<surname>Borden</surname>
  	<jobtitle>Assistant Professor</jobtitle>
  	<address>
		<affil>Tufts University School of Medicine</affil>
  		<subaffil>Department of Neurosurgery</subaffil>
		<aline>New England Medical Center #178</aline>
		<aline>750 Washington Street</aline>
		<city>Boston</city><state>MA</state>
		<postcode>02111</postcode>
		<phone>617-636-5859</phone>
		<fax>617-636-7587</fax>
		<email>jonathan@openhealth.org</email>
		<web>http://www.openhealth.org</web>
	</address>
  <bio><para>Dr. Jonathan Borden is an editor of the RDDL specification. 
  	He is the Director of the Open Healthcare Group, and a co-chair of the ASTM E31.25 XML Healthcare DTD subcommittee.</para></bio>
</author>
<keywords>
	<keyword>namespace</keyword>
	<keyword>RDDL</keyword>
	<keyword>XLink</keyword>
	<keyword>XHTML</keyword>
	<keyword>ontology</keyword>
</keywords>
<abstract>
	<para>
		A namespace is properly considered a collection of names. Namespaces while 
partitioned by a unique identifier, are properly the collection of names, 
not the partition. The <cit>XML Namespace recommendation</cit> defines a partition 
mechanism without defining the mechanism by which names are 
collected.
	</para>
	<para>
The Resource Directory Description Language (RDDL) was created to answer the 
question of what ought a namespace URI reference? RDDL uses an XHTML format in 
which resource elements are embedded. Each resource element contains a simple 
XLink referencing the related resource.
	</para>
	<para>
	The use of URIs as a mechanism of namespace partitioning has been controversial 
	and confusing for several reasons:
	<seqlist>
	<li><para>For the computer science community: XML namespaces differ from traditional namespaces as traditional namespaces conventionally refer to a <highlight style="ital">set</highlight> whereas XML namespaces more properly refer to an <highlight style="ital">unbounded partition</highlight></para></li>
	<li><para>For the web community: Use of URIs which can be resolved (i.e URLs) suggests that XML namespace identifiers 'point to something' yet no guidance is provided on what they ought reference.</para></li>
	</seqlist>
	</para>
<para>    RDDL is simple, solves both of these problems, and works with 
the current Web infrastructure.</para>
<para>The Resource Directory Description Language is an extension of <highlight style="ital">W3C XHTML Basic 1.0</highlight> with an added 
element named <highlight style="ital">resource</highlight>. This element serves 
as an XLink to the referenced resource, and contains a human-readable 
description of the resource and machine readable links which describe the 
purpose of the link and the nature of the resource being linked to. The nature 
of the resource being linked to is indicated by the <highlight style="ital">xlink:role</highlight> 
attribute and the purpose of the link is indicated by the 
<highlight style="ital">xlink:arcrole</highlight> attribute. </para>
<para>The rddl:resource element is defined as:</para>
<verbatim>&lt;!ELEMENT rddl:resource (#PCDATA | %Flow.mix;)*&gt;
&lt;!ATTLIST rddl:resource
  id            ID       #IMPLIED
  xml:lang      NMTOKEN  #IMPLIED
  xml:base      CDATA    #IMPLIED
  xmlns:rddl    CDATA    #FIXED   "http://www.rddl.org/"
  xlink:type    (simple) #FIXED   "simple"
  xlink:arcrole CDATA    #IMPLIED
  xlink:role    CDATA             "http://www.rddl.org/#resource"
  xlink:href    CDATA    #IMPLIED
  xlink:title   CDATA    #IMPLIED
  xlink:embed   CDATA    #FIXED   "none"
  xlink:actuate CDATA    #FIXED   "none"
  &gt;
</verbatim>
<p>For the computer science community,&nbsp;a proper 
namespace is created from an XML namespace as the <highlight style="bold">set</highlight> of 
fragment identifier qualified URI references contained in the RDDL document 
describing the XML namespace.</p>
<para>For the web community, a namespace name references a document which is 
readable by humans in popular browsers as well as providing machine readable 
links to resources related to the namespace. For example an "XML browser" would 
be able to locate code or plugins needed for the display of namespace qualified 
elements such as embedded SVG, MathML or other formats.</para>
<para>The RDDL specification itself serves as a RDDL description of the RDDL 
namespace URI <cit>http://www.rddl.org/</cit> . RDDL is 
described a DTD, and various schemata including RELAX, TREX, Schematron and XML 
Schema. In this context RDDL serves as a case study for the development and 
comparision of these various schema languages.</para>
<para>RDDL is now found at the end of the namespace URI for schema languages such 
as Schematron, XML Schema, and Examplotron, and for namespaces such as RSS 1.0, 
and the Comminity XSLT Extension effort.</para>
<para>Natures and purposes of namespace related resources are defined to be URI 
references according to XLink. RDDL defines common natures and purposes. A 
discussion of the RDDL ontology, use of RDDL to develop ontologies and 
integration of RDDL with RDF/DAML+OIL ontologies is discussed.</para>
</abstract>
</front>
<body>
  <section><title></title>
    <para></para>
  </section>
</body>
</paper>

